Mina Kirstein Curtiss Papers, 1913-2005
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Mina Kirstein Curtiss papers
1913-2005
Curtiss, Mina Kirstein, 1896-
MS 250
33 boxes (11 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
English professor, translator, and author. The bulk of the Curtiss papers focus on her writing career including correspondence with publishers and researchers, research material, artwork, and edited typescripts. Other materials include an oral history, photographs, diaries, and extensive correspondence with many eminent figures from the literary world as well as Smith College associates, friends and family members. Correspondents include Dean Acheson, Jacques Barzun, Jill Ker Conway, Anne Morrow Lindbergh, William Allen Neilson, Orson Welles, and Rebecca West.
Mina Kirstein Curtiss was born in Boston, Massachusetts on October 13, 1896 to Louis Kirstein, an optician, and Rose Stein. She had two younger brothers, Lincoln Kirstein, founder and general director of the New York City Ballet, and George Kirstein, publisher of the Liberal Weekly. The family moved to Rochester, NY in 1901 and remained there until 1912, when they returned to Boston and Louis Kirstein became a partner in Filene's Department Store. Curtiss was schooled at home by a governess until 1912, when she was sent to Northampton, Massachusetts to attend Miss Capen's School. She graduated from Smith College in 1918 and went on to earn an MA in English from Columbia University in 1920.
Prior to attending Columbia, Curtiss worked as a research clerk for Military Intelligence in Washington, D.C., from 1918 to 1920. She lived at the headquarters of the National Woman Suffrage Association where she became friends with Anna Howard Shaw and Carrie Chapman Catt. Curtiss married Henry Tomlinson Curtiss in 1926 only to be devastated by his untimely death a year later, in 1927. In 1933 she published The Midst of Life, a book that took the form of a series of letters to her dead husband. From 1922 to 1934 and again from 1940 to 1942, Curtiss was a beloved and highly regarded professor of English at Smith College, returning in 1976, at the age of 81, as Visiting Professor of English Language and Literature to teach a course on writing biography. From 1935 to 1939, she worked with Orson Welles and John Houseman in researching and writing scripts for the Mercury Theatre of the Air. In 1942, she created a program for the Des Moines Register and Tribune radio station, based on soldiers' letters home. This evolved into a book, Letters Home, edited by Curtiss and published in 1944. In 1942 Curtiss also joined the Office of War Information and, with Houseman, developed a short wave radio program for the BBC entitled "Answering You," in which celebrities responded to questions submitted by BBC listeners.
Rather than return to teaching when World War II ended, Curtiss opted to pursue a career in writing, authoring books, journal articles, and book reviews for national and international audiences. She was also fluent in French, and translated and edited works by several noted Frenchmen, including Edgar Degas, Philip Halevy, Marcel Proust, and Alexis Leger (also known as Saint-John Perse). She once said in an interview, "I fall in love with whatever I'm working on," and this passion, combined with a rigorous intellect, made her a tireless, tenacious, and meticulous researcher. Having read Proust and translated his letters for publication in the United States (The Letters of Marcel Proust, 1949), Curtiss was inspired to go to Paris to seek out Proust's family and friends still living, and to unearth more of his correspondence. This research led to publication in 1978 of Other People's Letters: A Memoir and to an interest in the composer Georges Bizet, which Curtiss pursued with characteristic vigor.
Following publication of Other People's Letters: A Memoir in 1978, Curtiss continued to write. She submitted several manuscripts for publication ("Winter Letters," a sequel to Midst of Life; "The Past and I" and "Slices of Life," sequential autobiographies; and "Plato: Archbishop of Moscow," a biographical sketch that evolved from researching A Forgotten Empress: Anna Ivanovich and Her Era, 1730-1740), and to her disappointment all were rejected. Despite a severe heart condition that left her bedridden for the last several years of her life, with the help of her secretary Curtiss continued to edit and modify the manuscripts in hopes that they would eventually go to press.
In addition to teaching and pursuing a career in writing, Curtiss was generous to causes in which she believed, to the extent that her finances allowed. In 1964, she donated most of the land that comprised Chapelbrook, her farm in Ashfield, Massachusetts, to the Trustees of Reservations, before selling the house and remaining acreage privately. She also founded the Chapelbrook Foundation the purpose of which was to provide funding to writers over the age of forty, to enable them to complete works in progress that might otherwise have gone unfinished. Curtiss also donated manuscript material to libraries and repositories, and works of art to museums.
In 1984, Smith College alumnae Anne Morrow Lindbergh and her sister, Constance Morrow Morgan, organized a campaign among Curtiss's former students to raise funds for a tribute to her. The response was overwhelming and led to establishment of the Mina Curtiss Fund, thanks to which a vase of fresh flowers, replaced on a regular basis in perpetuity, graces the Browsing Room in the William Allan Neilson Library at Smith College. Curtiss herself was an avid gardener and, not long before she died, suggested that the tribute take this form.
Mina Kirstein Curtiss died in Connecticut on October 31, 1985.
The Mina Kirstein Curtiss Papers consist of 11 linear feet and date from 1913 to 1986. Types of material include biographical information, including an oral history; personal and professional correspondence; photographs; journals and diaries; financial records; clippings; and typescripts of writings. The papers are arranged in six series: Biographical Material, Photographs, Correspondence, Teaching, Writings and Subject Files.
The bulk of the papers dates from 1933 to 1985 and focuses on Curtiss's writing career. It includes correspondence with publishers and researchers, research material, artwork, royalty statements, and typescripts. The typescripts are edited in Curtiss's hand and provide insight into her creative and analytical processes. Correspondence is also extensive and reflects the many friendships Curtiss developed while teaching, and in researching and writing her various books and attempting to see them through to publication. Many of the correspondents are people of note. The correspondence also well illustrates Curtiss's analytical approach to her topics of research.
Although the diaries and journals in this collection are limited in scope, they do reveal something of their author's passionate nature and discerning intellect, as well as some of her struggles and disappointments.
The photographs are also of interest, offering a glimpse into Curtiss's childhood and early family life, as well as life at Chapelbrook, the Curtiss home in Ashfield, Massachusetts.
The financial records document the acquisition of art and antiques, and the necessity for Curtiss to sell certain pieces later in her life, when she faced financial difficulties. They are also evidence of Curtiss's generosity in donating books, manuscript material and artwork to appropriate institutions when she was financially secure.
This collection is organized into five series:
I. Biographical Material
II. Photographs
III. Correspondence
IV. Teaching
V. Writings
VI. Subject Files
Oversize Materials; Microfilm; Books
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection. The John Houseman correspondence is photocopies of letters that are part of the John Houseman Papers in the Department of Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, University of California, Los Angeles. For copies and information about copyright, please contact UCLA.
History of the Collection
The Mina Kirstein Curtiss Papers were donated to the Sophia Smith Collection in 1986 by Kirstein's brothers, Lincoln and George Kirstein. Sallie Gottfried gave additional material in 1987, as did Lynne Robbins, co-executor of Mina Curtiss' estate, in 1988. In 1999, former student Delia Marshall donated a series of letters by Curtiss, spanning the years 1976 to 1985.
Search Terms
Acheson, Dean, 1893-1971--Correspondence; Auchincloss, Louis--Correspondence; Barzun, Jacques, 1907- --Correspondence; Bizet, Georges, 1838-1875; Conway, Jill K., 1934- --Correspondence; Curtiss family; Curtiss, Mina Kirstein, 1896-; Degas, Edgar, 1834-1917; Frankfurter, Felix, 1882-1965--Correspondence; Garnett, David, 1892- --Correspondence; Grant, Duncan, 1885-1978--Correspondence; Halevy, Daniel, 1872-1962--Correspondence; Houseman, John--Correspondence; Ivanovich, Anna; Kolb, Philip--Correspondence; Laski, Harold Joseph, 1893-1950--Correspondence; Levin, Harry, 1912- --Correspondence; Lindbergh, Anne Morrow, 1906- --Correspondence; Linscott, Robert Newton, 1886- --Correspondence; Manet, Edouard, 1832-1833; Neilson, William Allan, 1869-1946--Correspondence; Nicolson, Marjorie Hope, 1894- --Correspondence; Proust, Marcel, 1871-1922; Pope-Hennessy, John, Sir, 1834-1891--Correspondence; Saint-John Perse, 1887-1975; Steegmuller, Francis, 1906- --Correspondence; Storm, Hans Otto, 1895-1941--Correspondence; Untermeyer, Louis, 1885-1977--Correspondence; Welles, Orson, 1915- --Correspondence; West, Rebecca, Dame, 1892- --Correspondence; Europe--Description and travel--Sources; French literature--Translations into English--Sources; Mercury Theater of the Air--History--Sources; Radio broadcasting--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Smith College--Faculty--History--Sources; Smith College--Students--History--Sources; Women authors, American--20th century--Sources
Additional Information
Related Material
There is related material at the following institutions:
National Records and Archives Administration (NARA) -- recordings of the radio program Answering You
New York Public Library, Berg Collection -- letters to Mina K. Curtiss from British writers
New York Public Library, Dance Collection -- Lincoln Kirstein Papers and related documents
Pierpont Morgan Library, New York -- French books and manuscripts donated by Mina K. Curtiss, including letters by Edouard Manet
Smith College Archives -- material generated by Mina K. Curtiss when she was a student and, later, a professor at Smith College -- correspondence between Mina K. Curtiss and William Allan Neilson, and other Smith College colleagues
Smith College Mortimer Rare Book Room --Records of the Chapelbrook Foundation, a grant agency founded by Mina K. Curtiss 'which gave grants to writers over forty, to help them finish works in progress which they could not otherwise complete.'
University of California, Los Angeles -- letters to Mina K. Curtiss from John Houseman
University of Sussex at Brighton (UK) -- correspondence by Harold and Frida Laski
Yale University, Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library -- letters to Mina K. Curtiss from American writers
Yale University, Manuscripts and Archives, Sterling Memorial Library -- correspondence, photographs and travel diaries relating to Henry Tomlinson Curtiss
The previous owner of the collection prepared a microfilm edition of biographical clippings and correspondence that replicates approximately two-thirds of the collection. It is available through interlibrary loan and is accessible through an index of events and proper names.
The John Houseman correspondence is photocopies of letters that are part of the John Houseman Papers in the Department of Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, University of California, Los Angeles.
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL 1918-1986, 3 linear feet.
  This series provides an overview of Mina Kirstein Curtiss's private life and includes legal documents, an oral history, and photographs. The series also contains two bound volumes of poetry, some of which is in Curtiss's hand and the rest in another, unidentified hand. There is also correspondence pertaining to the Mina K.Curtiss Fund at Smith College, established in 1984. The financial information is extensive and includes tax returns; bills of sale, receipts, and appraisals for art and antiques; and records of donations made to various museums and libraries. Also included is a set of Curtiss's daily appointment calendars, spanning the years 1936 to 1985; the year 1939 is missing. There are also magazine articles, correspondence, drawings, legal documents, and printed matter relating to various properties Curtiss owned during her life, most of which concern Chapelbrook in Ashfield, Massachusetts. The Chapelbrook photograph albums are filed in this series because they are germane to to that particular property and because many of the photographs depict life there before Mina Stein Kirstein married Henry Tomlinson Curtiss in 1926.
- SERIES II. PHOTOGRAPHS
  This series consists of photo albums and single images of Mina Curtiss and her family; there are also several photographs of Henry Tomlinson Curtiss. Although most of the images are undated and the people in them are unidentified, they well illustrate certain aspects of Curtiss's family life and leisure activities.
- SERIES III. CORRESPONDENCE 1913-85, 1.75 linear feet.
  This series is divided into four subseries: Family, Friends and acquaintances, Legal and financial, and Miscellaneous. In the Family subseries, letters to "Goosie" and "Pettikins" probably refer to Lincoln and George Kirstein, respectively. The bulk of the series consists of Friends and acquaintances and includes letters from many eminent figures from the literary world. Letters to family and to Smith College President William Allan Neilson are especially revealing of Curtiss's thoughts and feelings as she grappled with personal problems. Legal and financial correspondence is comprised of letters between Curtiss and the prominent Boston firms that represented her legal and fiscal interests. Since Curtiss traveled extensively, whenever practicable on incoming correspondence her whereabouts have been noted in pencil above the greeting. (See also The Tin Box Collection: Letters of Roger Sessions and His Friends, Sarah Chapin, Ed., 1992).
- SERIES IV. TEACHING 1920-77, .25 linear feet.
  This series contains material relating to Mina K. Curtiss's years of teaching English at Smith College, and includes a grade book, lecture notes, and letters from students.
- SERIES V. WRITINGS 1917-85, 5.5 linear feet.
  This series consists of diaries and journals; draft manuscripts and typescripts; research materials; artwork for illustrating Curtiss's books; book reviews, both by Curtiss and by others about her books; journal articles; fan mail, and correspondence with publishers, literary agents, and research associates. A significant amount of material in this series relates to unpublished works. Some of the artwork filed under "Manet Caricatures: Olympia" was not actually used in the published version of that article, which appeared in the Massachusetts Review in 1966. It is unknown whether Curtiss decided against using this material in the "Olympia" article, or if she intended all along to use it in subsequent vignettes or in the proposed book on Manet caricatures. Since Curtiss filed this artwork with illustrations that were used in the "Olympia" article, it has been retained there.
  Material pertaining to The Midst of Life contains an untitled essay that Curtiss had identified as "background material--Midst of Life;" the essay has therefore been filed with other papers having to do with The Midst of Life. "Winter Letters," which never reached publication, was the sequel to The Midst of Life.
  "Slices of Life" is a sequel to the "Past and I." Both are autobiographies, neither of which was ever published. The manuscript "Platon: Archbishop of Moscow" was originally part of "Slices of Life," but Curtiss separated it and submitted it for publication, also unsuccessfully, as a separate manuscript; the "Platon" material is therefore filed immediately after the "Slices of Life" typescript.
  Much of the correspondence between Curtiss and Liliane Yacoel Ziegel, Curtiss's Parisian research associate, is in French, particularly that pertaining to Letters of Marcel Proust and Bizet and His World.
  Correspondence with publishers and literary agents comprises a separate subseries due to its broad and varied content, particularly the letters between Curtiss and Al Hart of the Fox Chase Agency.
  Research material for Letters Home consists of typescripts of letters soldiers wrote either to their hometown newspapers or to their families. Material pertaining to the radio program, "What's YOUR Idea," and to a column in Cosmopolitan called "Letters Home," both of which evolved from the huge success of Letters Home, is filed with other documents relating to the book.
- SERIES VI. SUBJECT FILES 1937-72, .25 linear feet.
  This series consists of translations of essays and a bibliography by Saint-John Perse, as well as clippings about him; and clippings about the murder of Elliot Speer, Headmaster of the Mount Hermon School for Boys, which occurred in September 1934.
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS
  - Biographical statements, Smith College transcript, and obituaries, 1918, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Birth and marriage certificates, passports, employment documents, clippings, and cemetery permits, 1921-83, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Wills, 1979-84, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bequests, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Mina K. Curtiss Fund at Smith College
    [See also SERIES III. CORRESPONDENCE]
    - General correspondence and lists of donors, 1984-85 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Vase design, correspondence, receipts, and drawings, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Letters of thanks by Mina K. Curtiss, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Responses to letters of thanks, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Condolences, 1985-86 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence re: estate of Mina K. Curtiss, 1985-86 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Oral history transcript, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Address books, circa 1985 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - French Legion of Honor award (includes medal), 1960 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Partnership agreement, The Nation, 1963-64 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Antiques, art, and furnishings
    - Correspondence, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Receipts and bills of sale, 1954-82, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Appraisals, 1965-1980, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence about Manet painting, 1974-82 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Photographs and negatives of unidentified paintings, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Notes on library of Mina K. Curtiss, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - List of books owned by Mina K. Curtiss (?) (incomplete), undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Books of poetry, 1922, undated (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - Poems found folded in books of poetry, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Financial records
    - Tax returns, 1939-43 (Box 3, Folder 1-5)
    - Social Security summary, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - List of income sources, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Account sheets for household staff, 1982-83 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Donations and gifts
    - Fondation St. John Perse: correspondence, 1975-85 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Pierpont Morgan Library: correspondence, 1968-84 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - New York Public Library: correspondence, 1964-84 (Box 3, Folder 11-13)
    - Sigmund Freud Archives: correspondence, 1962-73 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Smith College
      - William Allen Neilson Library
        - Correspondence, receipts, and reports, 1974-75 (Box 3, Folder 15)
      - Museum of Art
        - Correspondence, receipts, and reports, 1968-85, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
        - Estate of Mina K. Curtiss: correspondence, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 17)
        - Rare Book Room: correspondence and inventories, 1975-85 (Box 3, Folder 18)
      - College Archives and Sophia Smith Collection
        - Margaret Storrs Grierson: correspondence, 1947-64 (Box 3, Folder 19)
        - College Archives: correspondence and inventories,1983-84 (Box 3, Folder 20)
        - Sophia Smith Collection: correspondence re: estate of Mina K. Curtiss, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 21)
      - Other institutions: correspondence and inventories, 1944-83 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Calendars
    - 1936-38, 1940-52 (Box 4, Folder 1-16)
    - 1953-71 (Box 5, Folder 1-19)
    - 1972-85 (Box 6, Folder 1-15)
  - Residences
    - Chapelbrook, Ashfield, Massachusetts
      - Photograph albums, 1917-29, undated (Box 7)
      - Publications
        - House Beautiful, 1924 (Box 8, Folder 1)
        - House and Garden, 1925, 1946 (Box 8)
      - Management plans, 1977, undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
      - Correspondence, 1979-85 (Box 8, Folder 3)
      - Elevation and brochure, undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - Inventories, 1924, undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
      - A Climber's Guide to Chapel Falls, circa 1979 (Box 8, Folder 6)
      - Brochures, Trustees of Reservations, 1981, undated (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Bethel and Weston, Connecticut houses: descriptive brochure, Certificates of Title, Mortgage Deed, correspondence, photograph, and financial information, 1963-78, undated (Box 8)
- SERIES II. PHOTOGRAPHS
  - Mina Curtiss, alone and with family and friends, undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Henry T. Curtiss, Smith College, and miscellaneous, 1916-18 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Photograph album, undated (Box 10)
- SERIES III. CORRESPONDENCE
  - Family
    - Louis Kirstein, 1913-37, undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Rose Stein Kirstein, 1942-52 (Box 11, Folder 2-3)
    - George Kirstein ("Pettikins?") and Lincoln Kirstein ("Goosie?"), 1947-49, 1971 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Friends and acquaintances
    - A, 1978 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Acheson, Dean and Alice, 1928-85 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Adams, Thomas B., 1967-84 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Adams, William H., 1985 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Auchincloss, Louis, 1978 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - B, 1930-78 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Barzun, Jacques, 1951-57 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Bradley, Jenny, 1947-78 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - C, 1978-84 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Cain, Julien, 1959-61 (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - Conway, Jill Ker, 1975-85 (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - D, 1965, 1982 (Box 11, Folder 16)
    - E, 1985 (Box 11, Folder 17)
    - Einstein, Albert, 1946-47 (Box 11, Folder 18)
    - F, 1982-84, undated (Box 11, Folder 19)
    - Fardig, Elenor, 1958-69, undated (Box 11, Folder 20)
    - Fistere, Isobel, 1978-83, undated (Box 11, Folder 21)
    - Frankfurter, Felix, 1943-44, undated (Box 11, Folder 22)
    - G, 1967, 1978 (Box 11, Folder 23)
    - Garnett, David, 1947 (Box 11, Folder 24)
    - Gottfried, Sallie, 1982-85 (Box 11, Folder 25)
    - Grant, Duncan (photocopies), 1923-25 (Box 11, Folder 26)
    - Green, Dorothy, 1947-60 (Box 11, Folder 27)
    - Guerin, Jacques, 1947-49 (Box 11, Folder 28)
    - H, 1979 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Halevy, Daniel, 1954-58, undated (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Houseman, John, 1936-54, [primarily photocopies of correspondence in the John Houseman Papers, Department of Special Collections, Charles E. Young Library, University of California, Los Angeles] (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Johnson, Hugh, 1942-44 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - K, 1926, 1976, undated (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Kolb, Philip, 1947-78 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Krauss, Henry, 1968-69 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Laski, Frida, 1919-22 (Box 12, Folder 8-10)
    - Laski, Harold, 1922 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - L'Engle, Madeleine, 1980 (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - Levin, Harry, 1946-59, undated (Box 12, Folder 13)